Dave Lotito

Data Scientist, Assistant Vice President

Professional Data Scientist at Citizens Financial Group with more than 3.5 years of experience analyzing large data sets and developing data driven solutions for Fortune 500 companies. Involved in various projects where I have led multiple teams to success.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist, Advanced Analytics

June 2020 - Present

Citizens, Providence, RI

- Spearheaded the creation of the banks first OCR (Optical Character Recognition) machine learning software for the acquisition and transition of HSBC consumer banking customers. Software successfully extracted, predicted, and identified letters & digits in FDIC Trust and FDIC Signature Card documents with near perfect accuracy. Software saved the organization ~\$500k & reduced manual intervention.
- Leveraged AWS Textract low-level client for detecting and analyzing text in documents to convert the text into machine-readable output for Citizens FDIC joint signature card document extraction for millions of documents.
- Managed the banks' consumer collections models, helping implement the various model control points needed to mitigate risk and identify issues.
- Created a data validation pipeline in Amazon SageMaker using
 Python to streamline the EDA process & check for data anomalies ensuring our data is clean and ready for modeling.
- Created, improved, and maintained the LIBOR Sourcing python-based applications. Each day review Jira for user stories based on business needs and new requirements.
- Developed the missing documents python-based application to account for documents that weren't found in our sourcing code but were in-scope documents that the business team would need to manually retrieve. The script successfully accounted for >1,000 missing documents that were needed for the LIBOR transition initiative.

Business Strategy & Operations

May 2019 - August 2019

Fidelity Investments · Internship, Merrimack, NH

- Collaborated effectively within an Agile team, tackling diverse projects, and skillfully addressing intricate business analysis challenges within the PI / CCP framework to enhance customer service.
- Devised a comprehensive strategy by consolidating data, enabling the calculation of the distribution of financial advisor and relationship manager associates across Fidelity branches. This strategy proved pivotal in orchestrating the WIN10 / Outlook migration.
- Employed SQL proficiency to conduct a thorough analysis of both incoming and outgoing emails, resulting in the identification and resolution of communication routing issues among associates and clients. This initiative significantly streamlined communication processes.

CONTACT

- · Providence, RI
- 978-973-4253
- · DavidJLotito@gmail.com
- www.linkedin.com/in/david-lotito
- · github.com/davelotito

SKILLS

Data Visualization/Engineering:

- Tableau
- Sisense
- Plotly
- Matplotlib

Techniques:

- · Hypothesis Testing
- Classification
- · Linear Regression
- · Anomaly Detection
- Neural Networks
- Resampling Methods

Tools and Frameworks:

- AWS (SageMaker, Athena, S3)
- Python (Numpy, Pandas, Keras, TensorFlow, Keras, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Sklearn)
- R (ggplot, dplyr, tidyr, plotly, knitr)
- · Databases (MySQL)
- Excel

EDUCATION

Boston University

MSc, Applied Data Analytics Boston, MA — September 2022 — May 2024

University of Massachusetts, Lowell

BSc, Management Information Systems & Marketing Analytics Lowell, MA — September 2016 - May 2020

CERTIFICATES

- Python for Data Science & Machine Learning
- Tableau Data Analytics & Visualization
- Advanced Deep Learning with Keras & Image Processing